New York StateWide Senior Action Council; Records apap111
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York Statewide Senior Action Council Records
1974-2001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap111
14.05 cubic ft.
The New York StateWide Senior Action Council records document the issues faced by senior citizens in New York State over the course of almost three decades. The bulk of the records consist of subject files in the areas of health care, Medicare, and social security issues. In addition to topical material, these records document the fundraising activities of the organization and its various sub-groups. Notably included are publications issued by the organization, including the Sentinel newsletter (1992-1996) and the Senior Action newspaper (1977-1991). The bulk of the material, found in the subject files, is useful for documenting issues about which NYSSAC was active. NYSSAC's work with New York state legislators, as well as government and private agencies in advocating for seniors and social justice issues, and their outreach efforts in education and advocacy, are well documented throughout the collection. Records of the activities of Executive Directors Michael Burgess and Bonnie Ray are the most prominent in the collection.
Administrative History
The New York StateWide Senior Action Council (NYSSAC) is a grassroots membership organization made up of individual senior citizens and senior citizen clubs from all parts of New York State. NYSSAC was organized in 1972 from War on Poverty funds with the goal of developing a statewide organization of older New Yorkers who could advocate for their interests and needs regarding services, programs and policies effecting older persons. NYSSAC's unique history and role has been to focus on the needs of low-income and minority seniors. Although there have been some revisions of the organizational by-laws through the years (see Chronology), the mission of NYSSAC has remained constant.
The New York StateWide Senior Action Council Mission statement:
To achieve through united action the dignity, well-being and security of all senior citizens of New York State
To provide a unified and articulate voice on behalf of older New Yorkers, especially as advocate for the low-income elderly and low-income persons of all generations
To promote the general well-being of the aging through educational processes outlining the legislative needs of the elderly
To promote the best interest of children and youth by intergenerational programs of mutual support
To develop in the community an awareness of the needs and the capabilities of older persons
To help develop the leadership abilities of the elderly through leadership training and skills utilization
To monitor programs and services to the elderly of New York State to ensure their full representation and participation in planning, implementation and evaluation. [New York StateWide Senior Action Council: Older New Yorkers' Grassroots Advocacy Voice Since 1972. 6/18/03. www.nysenior.org/About_StateWide. 6/19/03].
As of 2001, in addition to the core senior action council, NYSSAC is comprised of several other branches targeting specific issues facing seniors; these include the Patients' Rights Project which sponsors the Patient's Hotline and deals with Peer Review Organizations (PRO) and Diagnosis Related Groups (DRG) issues; the Supplemental Security Income (SSI) Advocacy Group with 50 groups statewide, and the Rural Senior Health Organizing Project (RSHOP). NYSSAC also consists of satellite Regional Councils that work in association with the statewide council in Albany.
Throughout the 1970s and 1980s, NYSSAC has worked on a number of issues and provided trainings and educational workshops throughout the state. In its first decade (1972-1982), NYSSAC addressed issues affecting low-income seniors, through outreach and advocacy training in areas that included Food Stamps; Supplemental Security Income (SSI); Energy Assistance Programs, and the Senior Citizen Crime Victim and Prevention Program.
Throughout the 1980s, NYSSAC played a key role in advocating for laws ending mandatory retirement and enacting the Elderly Pharmaceutical Insurance Coverage (EPIC) program. In 1986, Rose Kryzak (1900-1999) led senior activists in a march on Governor Cuomo's office, demanding action on EPIC legislation. In 1988, NYSSAC used a New York Foundation grant to fund the Development and Restructuring Project, aimed at making NYSSAC financially self sufficient for basic operations. At the same time, the Rural Senior Health Organizing Project (RSHOP) under the direction of Joan Butcher, expanded operations and conducted research with grants from the Campaign for Human Development (CHD).
During the 1990s NYSSAC continued to be active primarily in promoting health care issues relevant to seniors. The health care reform battles of the early 1990s generated a large body of records pertaining to the Clinton Health Plan, Single-Payer Plans. The Patient's Rights Project became very active on issues pertaining to Diagnosis Related Groups (DRGs) and Peer Review Organizations, particularly after the 1995 appointment of Bonnie Ray as Health Care Advocate. Likewise, the RSHOP continued to work with the Campaign for Human Development throughout the 1990s.
The 1995 reappointment of Michael Burgess as Executive Director and the appointment of Bonnie Ray as Health Care Advocate led to new focuses for NYSSAC. The failure of the Clinton Health Plan and entrenchment of the HMO system has made issues such as the Patient's Bills of Rights, DRG reform, and PRO management, important targets of NYSSAC's action.
Chronology:
1972 New York StateWide Senior Action Council formed with War on Poverty funds.
1982 Michael Burgess becomes executive director.
1986 New York StateWide Senior Action Council campaign results in passage of Elderly Pharmaceutical Insurance Coverage Program (EPIC) to pay for prescription drugs for low-income seniors.
1987 Michael Burgess resigns as executive director. Bonnie Ray assumes post as Executive Director. Patient Advocacy Project established with funding from a Citizen Action Grant.
1988 NYSSAC undertakes a Development and Restructuring Project to make the organization financially self-sufficient for basic operation. Project funded by a New York Foundation Grant. Revisions of original NYSSAC By-laws adopted on September 27, 1988.
1988-1989 The Rural Senior Health Organizing Project conducts a two year study on rural health conditions in 12 counties in New York State, funded by a Campaign for Human Development Grant.
1988-1990 Michael Burgess serves on Peer Review Organization Liaison Committee.
1989 Donna Rudinski named Development Director for NYSSAC.
1990 Rose Kryzak Legacy Fund created in honor of senior activist Rose Kryzak's 90th birthday. Interest from this fund is used to provide support to low-income seniors to participate in training conferences, and advocacy activities. Michael Burgess helps negotiate contract for Island Peer Review Organization.
1995 Michael Burgess resumes post as executive director. Bonnie Ray assumes post as health care advocate.
1972 New York StateWide Senior Action Council formed with War on Poverty funds.
1982 Michael Burgess becomes executive director.
1986 New York StateWide Senior Action Council campaign results in passage of Elderly Pharmaceutical Insurance Coverage Program (EPIC) to pay for prescription drugs for low-income seniors.
1987 Michael Burgess resigns as executive director. Bonnie Ray assumes post as Executive Director. Patient Advocacy Project established with funding from a Citizen Action Grant.
1988 NYSSAC undertakes a Development and Restructuring Project to make the organization financially self-sufficient for basic operation. Project funded by a New York Foundation Grant. Revisions of original NYSSAC By-laws adopted on September 27, 1988.
1988-1989 The Rural Senior Health Organizing Project conducts a two year study on rural health conditions in 12 counties in New York State, funded by a Campaign for Human Development Grant.
1988-1990 Michael Burgess serves on Peer Review Organization Liaison Committee.
1989 Donna Rudinski named Development Director for NYSSAC.
1990 Rose Kryzak Legacy Fund created in honor of senior activist Rose Kryzak's 90th birthday. Interest from this fund is used to provide support to low-income seniors to participate in training conferences, and advocacy activities. Michael Burgess helps negotiate contract for Island Peer Review Organization.
1995 Michael Burgess resumes post as executive director. Bonnie Ray assumes post as health care advocate.
Scope and Contents
The New York StateWide Senior Action Council records document the issues faced by senior citizens in New York State throughout the late 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s. The bulk of the records consist of topical subject files related to issues about which the activists in NYSSAC were concerned, particularly health care, Medicare, and social security issues. In addition to topical material, these records document the fundraising activities of the organization and its various sub-groups. Also included are publications issued by the organization, including the Sentinel newsletter (1992-1996) and the Senior Action newspaper (1977-1991).
The collection is particularly strong in documenting issues involving Medicare, Long-Term Care, DRGs, and PRO issues. Series 4: Subject Files; Sub-series 1: Health Care/Medicare, includes source material, news clippings, articles, and supporting material documenting these issues, with particularly strong material dating from 1985-2000. Sub-series 2: Senior Advocacy, of the same series, includes a strong set of materials relative to SSI (Supplemental Security Income).
The bulk of the material, found in Series 4: Subject Files, is useful for documenting issues about which NYSSAC was active over the course of almost three decades. There is limited material from the first ten years (1972-1982) of the organization and relatively little material from the years immediately prior to the accession of this material in 2001. NYSSAC's work with New York state legislators, both Government and private agencies advocating for Seniors and social justice issues, and their outreach efforts in education and advocacy, are well documented throughout the collection. Records of the activities of Executive Directors Michael Burgess and Bonnie Ray are the most prominent in the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into five series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the New York StateWide Senior Action Council in February 2001.
Related Materials
Related material, including material created by NYSSAC is available in the Helen Quirini Papers (APAP-102) in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Senior Citizens; Medicine and Health Care; Senior power--New York (State); Older people--New York (State)--Political activity; Age discrimination--New York (State); Older people-- Abuse of--New York (State); Correspondence; Grant proposals; Clippings; Photographs; Memorabilia; Press Releases; Bylaws; Newsletters; Newspapers; Floppy discs; Burgess, Michael; Butcher, Joan; Harenberg, Paul; Kyryzak, Rose; Ray, Bonnie; New York StateWide Senior Action Council
- Administrative Records, 1975-1997; 1; 1.74 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  These records, located within the following sub-series, document the administrative functions of the organization. They include extensive information on grants, budgets, and other fiscal information. In addition, they contain some information about personnel within the organization. Folders containing correspondence will be found throughout the series.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Fundraising, 1983-1996; 1.1; 0.50 cubic ft.
    These records document the general fundraising activities of NYSSAC. Consisting primarily of grant applications and related documents for funding of general expenses, they also include information on projects that were not funded and therefore did not generate any further records. Fiscal statistics, articles on NYSSAC activity and correspondence pertaining to fundraising are also found here. Specific projects' fundraising activities are documented in the sub-series relating to them. Prominent grantors include Chemical Bank, New York Foundation, and the Campaign for Human Development Foundation.
    Arranged alphabetically and then chronologically
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Applications, 1983; 1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 1)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Applications, 1985-1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 2)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Applications for "Older New Yorkers' Alternative Media Project", 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 3)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Pre-Application, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 4)
    - Chemical Bank, Grant Applications, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 5)
    - Chemical Bank, Grant Applications, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 6)
    - Community Services Block Grant Advisory Council, 1983-1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 7-9)
    - Donations for Rose Kryzak Tribute Publication, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 10)
    - Families USA, Discretionary Grant, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 11)
    - Food Stamp Project Proposal, 1984-1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 12)
    - Foundation Proposals, Miscellaneous, 1985-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 13)
    - Fundraising Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 14)
    - Fundraising, Miscellaneous Materials, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 15)
    - Grant Proposal for Development and Reorganization Project, 1989-1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 16)
    - Grants, General Information on Sources, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 17)
    - Grants, "National Guide to Funding in Aging", 2nd edition, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 18)
    - Hands Across America, Grant Proposal, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 19)
    - Loan Agreement, Key Bank, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 20)
    - Mohawk-Hudson Community Foundation, Applications, 1987; 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 21)
    - Narratives Provided to Funding Agencies, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 22)
    - New York City Department for Aging, Contractor Performance Evaluation, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 23)
    - New York City Department for Aging, Registration and Grant Applications, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 24)
    - New York Department of Health, Proposal for AIDS Education, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 25)
    - New York Foundation Grant, Application and Reports, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 26)
    - New York Foundation Grant, Application and Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 27)
    - Research Project, State University of New York at Buffalo, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 28)
    - Telemarketing Proposal, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 29)
    - United Way Pledge, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 30)
    - Villers Foundation, Grants, 1988; 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 31)
  - Intergenerational Unity Project, 1992-1995; 1.2; 0.17 cubic ft.
    These records document the Intergenerational Unity Project, a project initiated by NYSSAC and funded primarily by a New York Foundation Grant. The aim of the project was to bridge the gaps between youth activists and senior activists in an attempt to forge a single voice. Records consist of grant applications and proposals, correspondence, and membership campaign material.
    - Intergenerational Unity Project, Grant Proposals, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 32)
    - New York Foundation, Final Report, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 33)
    - New York Foundation, Grant Application and Reports, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 34)
    - New York Foundation, Grant Correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 35)
    - New York Foundation, Grant Proposal Materials, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 36)
    - New York Foundation, Grant Reports, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 37)
    - Membership Campaign, Material, 1993-1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 38)
  - Office Records, 1975-1997; 1.3; 0.25 cubic ft.
    These records document administrative work associated with managing and running the organization. They include a variety of materials, including office leases, fiscal records, personnel files and several photographs of Bonnie Ray at public events.
    - Applicants for Administrative Assistant, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 39)
    - Budget, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 40)
    - Budget, 1989-1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 41)
    - By-laws, 1986; 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 42)
    - By-laws, Drafts of Proposed Changes, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 43)
    - Events Announcements, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 44)
    - Financial Audit, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 45)
    - KEX Copysource Lease Agreement, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 46)
    - Mailing List Addresses, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 47)
    - Membership Lists, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 48)
    - New York State Senior Advocates, Certificate of Incorporation Form, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 49)
    - New York State Unemployment Insurance, 1983-1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 50)
    - Office Lease Agreement, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 51)
    - Pinpoint Communications, Software Co., 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 52)
    - Ray, Bonnie, Application Correspondence and Appointment, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 53)
    - Ray, Bonnie, Personal File, 1986-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 54)
    - Ray, Bonnie, Supervisor's Workshop, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 55)
    - Senior Citizens Action Council, 1975-1981 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 56)
    - Tax Exempt Certificate, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 57)
  - Patients' Rights Project, 1987-1996; 1.4; 0.40 cubic ft.
    These records document the administration of the NYSSAC Patients' Rights Project. This was an ongoing effort to act as a health care advocate for seniors and other patients. The project deals specifically with Medicare and Medicaid claims disputes, DRG discharge disputes, but also deals with other common problems, promoting a patients' rights hotline, an informational hotline, and legal advocacy. Records include grant applications and background materials, correspondence, and a final report on the DRG Monitoring Project/Complaint Line at Community Action for Legal Services (CALS).
    - Chase Manhattan Bank, Grant Application, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 1)
    - Chemical Bank, Grant Application, 1995 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 2)
    - Citizen Action Grant, 1987-1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 3)
    - Citizen Action, Regional Advocacy Projects, 1997 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 4)
    - Clark Foundation, Funding Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 5)
    - Diagnosis Related Groups (DRG) Education Project Funding, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 6)
    - DRG Education Project Funding, Proposal and Reports, 1990-1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 7)
    - DRG Monitoring Project, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 8)
    - Legislative Budget Proposal, 1988-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 9)
    - Legislative Budget Proposal, 1989-1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 10)
    - Legislative Budget Proposal, 1990-1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 11)
    - Legislative Budget Request, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 12)
    - Legislative Budget Request, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 13)
    - Legislative Budget Request, 1994 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 14)
    - Legislative Budget Request, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 15)
    - Long Term Care Proposal, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 16)
    - New York State Office for the Aging, Grant, 1988-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 17)
    - North Star Fund, 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 18)
    - Patient Advocacy Project, Materials, 1987-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 19)
    - "Your Rights as a Hospital Patient" Booklet, 1994 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 20)
  - Regional Councils, 1991-1994; 1.5; 0.05 cubic ft.
    These records document some of the work of the NYSSAC regional councils; local grassroots groups working in tandem with NYSSAC on issues pertinent to particular regions of the state.
    - Region Six, Lewis County Staff, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 21)
    - Region Six, Meetings, 1990; 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 22)
    - Statewide Regional Lists, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 23)
    - Stevens, James, President of Region Five, 1993-1994 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 24)
  - Rural Senior Health Organizing Project, 1988-1991; 1.6; 0.37 cubic ft.
    These records document the administration of the Rural Senior Health Organizing Project, a collaborative effort involving NYSSAC and representatives from the rural regions of New York State. The project was funded primarily by the Campaign for Human Development (CHD) Grant. The records include information on the grant and the requisite Quarterly Reports submitted to the funder as well as the correspondence and files of Rural Heath Project Director, Joan Butcher.
    Arranged alphbetically and then chronologically
    - Butcher, Joan, Correspondence and Reports, 1989-1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 25)
    - Butcher, Joan, Correspondence and Reports, 1989-1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 26)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Agreements, 1989-1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 27)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Application, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 28)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Application, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 29)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Application, 1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 30)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Information, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 31)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Proposal, 1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 32)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Proposal, 1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 33)
    - Campaign for Human Development, Grant Proposal, Drafts, 1988-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 34)
    - Correspondence With Campaign for Human Development, 1990 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous, 1988-1989 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 36)